Augur and Hitchcock Family papers
Connecticut Historical Society
Augur and Hitchcock Family Papers
1822-1869
Connecticut Historical Society, Hartford, Connecticut
Augur family.
0.25 linear foot (1/2 box)
Biographical Sketch
Daniel Page Augur (d. 1834) of New Haven, Connecticut, married Hannah Smith (1781-1868). He was a commander with the Revenue Cutter service from 1812 until his death at Key West in 1824. Their daughter Caroline (1804-1884) married Sheldon Hitchcock (1804-1877), a shoemaker by trade. Their eldest son, Charles Augustus (b. 1829) moved to Chicago where he was superintendent of the Union Brass Works. Caroline and Sheldon Hitchcock’s second son Frank Benjamin (b. 1841) served in the 13th Regiment, Connecticut Volunteer Infantry from 1861-1865.
Horace August Augur, eldest son of Daniel and Hannah, was a cabinetmaker. He moved to Lima, Peru in 1826 and remained there until 1830. Daniel and Hannah’s other children included Daniel (b. 1811), William Henry (b. 1814), Edward (b. 1818) and Mary Ann (b. 1824).
Scope and Content
The collection, donated to the CHS in 1988, consists primarily of correspondence and diaries or journals. Papers are arranged according to individual and then organized alphabetically.
Daniel Augur wrote letters to his daughter and son-in-law, Caroline and Sheldon Hitchcock, 1830, 1833, with news of his activities and comments on religion. He also kept a logbook while aboard the Revenue Cutter Dexter in 1833, of which a manuscript copy survives. Horace A. Augur wrote to his sister Caroline in 1828 from Lima, Peru. Mary Ann Augur kept a religious diary from 1822 to 1823.
Charles A. Hitchcock is represented in the collection by two letters written to his father, one in 1857 notifying him of the death of Charles’ wife Mary. Frank Hitchcock regularly wrote to his parents while was serving with the 13th Regiment of Connecticut Volunteers as a sergeant in Company C. His letters, describing camp life, were addressed from Louisiana, Virginia and Georgia.
Sheldon Hitchcock’s letters to his wife Caroline are dated thirty years apart. In 1833-34 he was aboard the Revenue Cutter Dexter with his father-in-law Daniel Augur. He told Caroline that he did not want to return to making shoes (in 1860 his occupation is listed as boot maker). His 1834 letter described Captain Daniel’s death. In 1869, Sheldon wrote from Chicago, where he apparently went for his health. Two copies of an 1840 diary, written primarily in Wilmington, North Carolina, appear to be the property of Sheldon Hitchcock. He was engaged in coastal shipping, perhaps in an attempt to avoid returning to making shoes.
The final folder in the collection contains an interesting assortment of documents, two of which warrant a note. An acrostic on the verso of an undated letter spells out the names Lucy Mansfield and Hannah Stillman. A chromolithograph certificate notes that Sarah Hitchcock was a member of the Bethany Aide Society, 1866.
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the collection.
Accruals
The collection is closed.
Subject Headings
Personal Names
Augur, Daniel, d. 1834.; Augur, Horace, b. 1804.; Augur, Mary Ann, b. 1824; Hitchcock, Frank, b. 1841; Hitchcock, Sheldon, 1804-1877
Family Names
Augur family.; Hitchcock family.
Corporate Names
United States. Army. Connecticut Infantry. Regiment 13th (1862-1866).
Contents:
- Augur-Hitchcock Papers
  - Daniel Augur, letters, 1830,1833 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Daniel Augur, ship’s log, 1833 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Horace Augur, letters, 1822,1828 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Mary Ann Augur, religious diary, 1822-1823 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Frank Hitchcock, letters, 1862-1866 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Charles Hitchcock, letters, 1857,1858 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Sheldon Hitchcock, letters, 1833-1834, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sheldon Hitchcock, diary, 1840-1841 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Assorted documents, 1823, 1854, 1866, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)